Hello, everyone!
Branching is one of the most important concepts of modern git. Branch is actually
an isolated flow of development, that can have its own commits, so that they are invisible to other branches.
In this video I'm going to briefly show its usage and starting from the next one we are going to have some practical examples
Branches are with us from the very beginning of the project
As soon as we make our first commit git creates the very first branch which is called master.
Firther on we can ignore that and make more and more commits, actually, develop our project.
Now imagine for a moment that we have an idea of a cool feature.
But the feature is quite big and needs time to accomplish so we can only work on it from time to time
and till its done, we dont want to mix it into the main stable code of the project.
This is exactly where branches are extremely helpful, as we can stay in the same project,
same repository, create a new branch and call it "feature"
git has a concept of current branch, the branch you are working in at the moment
So we are making this "feature" branch our current branch and committing all the code into it.
First commit, second commit and so on. Git allows us to easilly switch between the branches so we can go back to our
main "master" branch, that corresponds to the previous state of the project, before this new feature is committed
and continue the development. Then we can add some new feature code
and switch back to master.
If new idea didnt work out we can always delete the whole "feature" branch, without ever affecting
the "master" branch, where all the stable code is residing. But I hope, that most of the time
new changes are great and when we are done with the new feature we can merge it to our stable "master" branch
This kind of development approach when we have a separate branch per feature and merge it to stable when its ready,
is called "feature branching"
We can have multiple branches, where we develop different features in parallel
like "feature" and "another feature"
Different branches can be developed by different people
e.g I'm working on a "feature" and my colleague is working on "another-feature" and we dont collide with each other, because each one of us is developing in their own branch
But if I want to check what was my colleague been up to I can easilly switch to his branch
get through the code, maybe, even fix something or leave a comment and then go back. So, the concept of branches prooves to be very
helpful for teams.
Of course, its not the only way to use branches
another common approach is to use branches to keep several parallel versions of the project
Same as previous example, making a commit, another commit
then we decide to release, and there are a lot of things todo
so we have to decide which ones are going to be the part of release and which ones are to be the features of the next releases.
We are making a new branch for the new release and call it "1.0". From now on our development is split into 2 branches.
We are going to work on new features in the "master" branch and "1.0" will host all the features that
are making it into the release.
Now I'm
switching to the "1.0" branch or give it to my colleague and they commit into it, another one, making it ready for the release
And as git allow us to switch between the branches there can be an ongoing development of new features in "master"
Of course we can have an issue that existed
before we split and we have to fix it in both "1.0" and "master".
Lets fix the issue in one of the branches. Most of the time its fixed in "master" first
For example, lets assume this commit is our fix. Then git allows us to do so-called "cherry-pick", that is taking any commit
and apply it to the other branch, like "1.0" in our case. In the end the issue will be fixed in both branches and we continue
the development of new features. But now its time to release a version "2.0".
We are making a separated branch for it
where we polish the features that are going to be a part of the version 2.0. And master will have all the new features for later releases
and so on
So, branches allow to have several versions of the project in the same repository,
switch between them and develop each feature independently. We can create any number of branches starting with any commit
for example: branch "1.0" can have a "1.1" branch
these branches as above are called the "release branches" and this is another example of how one can use the branches
apart of the general usage we saw earlier
Its important to understand, that git on its own doesn't require one to create branches at all
some projects can only use feature-branches and some can only use release branches
some can use both. Theres a well-known strategy of how to use both approaches together known as "git flow"
You can use all of this and for that we are getting to some practical usage of git branching on the example of
the particular git repository